Wait until Your Majesty
ついに陛下にまで及んだ
Surrenders Xie Xuan, then he'll come
謝玄を差し出せそうすれば彼は戻ってくる
By then
その時に
No one can fault him
誰も彼の欠点を言えない
Enough
いいよ
My general
私の将軍
If I use him
私は使える
I trust him
信じてみよう
Order Zhu Yuanzhi
命は朱元之
To rescue the emperor
勤王
Yes
はい
The 21st year of Longwu
隆武二十一年
Zhu Yuanzhi led troops to rescue the emperor
朱元之は軍を率いて勤王した
In less than half a month
しかし半月しか経っていない
He pierced through the western aristocratic coalition
西路の士族連合軍を突き破る
Then launched a lightning strike on the southern commander's camp
そして南方の主将の本営を急襲した
Personally beheaded the rebel general
彼は反乱軍の将軍たちを直接斬首した
The eastern route scattered like birds and beasts upon hearing the news
東の道で風の音を聞くと鳥や獣が散り散りになる
The great families submitted memorials begging for mercy
多くの士族が次々と上奏して許しを求めた
Zhu Yuanzhi
朱元之
The rebels are now pacified
反乱が平定された
Why aren't you wearing court robes?
なぜ朝服を着ないのですか
Wearing armor in court
甲冑を着て殿に上がるよ
Right
そうだね
This is
これは
Well said
その通りだよ
Otherwise, Minister Wang
さもなければ王様
How about going to the front to fight for me?
私の代わりに前線で戦ってくれませんか
In the court
朝廷の上
General Zhu, please be careful with your words
朱将軍言葉に注意してください
Don't think
思わないで
I don't know how you
私はあなたたちを知りません
Talk about me behind my back
私のことを裏でどう言っているのか
If not for concern for Your Majesty's safety
もし陛下の安全を考慮しなければ
Would I have rushed through the night
私は徹夜で突撃できる
To save you gossiping women?
あなたたちのようなおしゃべりな女たちを助けに来たのですか
You
お前これ
And some of you
それにあなたたちの中の何人かも
I don't care how you fight behind the scenes
私はあなたたちが舞台の下でどう争おうと構わない
Whoever dares involve Your Majesty
誰が陛下に関わることを敢えてするのか
Better think carefully
心の中でよく考えてみて
Who has such great resentment?
誰がこんなに恨みを持っているの
Kowtow to Your Majesty
天皇陛下に拝謁する
We pay respects to Your Majesty
私たちは陛下に拝謁いたします
You've worked hard
お疲れ様です
General Zhu
朱将軍
Your Majesty is well
陛下ご健康でありますように
I am not tired
私は苦労しません
Read
念
General Zhu Yuanzhi of Zhenbei
鎮北将軍朱元之
Loyalty and courage bestowed by heaven
忠勇天授
Merits illustrious
勲功が顕著である
Rescued the emperor and quelled rebellion
勤王と乱の鎮圧
Merit surpassing all officials
功績を群臣に冠する
Now specially promoted to Grand General
今特進大将軍
Envoy with credentials, bearer of the Yellow Axe
節を持ち仮の黄鉞を使う
Commander of all military affairs
中外の諸軍事を統率する都督
Granted the Nine Bestowments as special honor
錫は九錫の殊礼によって
May enter court without hurrying
朝貢に赴かない
Addressed without name
名を崇拝しない
May wear sword and shoes in court
剣を履いて殿に上る
Opened a ministry equal to the Three Excellencies
開府儀同三司
I
しん
Kowtow in gratitude for Your Majesty's grace
陛下のご恩に深く感謝申し上げます